Kill? Kill!
杀人？杀人！
-Sh… Shion-dono! -Nurugai!
-士…士远大人 -濡亥
Use your sword to cut deep into the flowers and roots.
用你的剑深深地切入花朵和根部
We might be able to stop his transformation.
或许我们能够阻止他的转化
-Then take everyone and get out of here. -Got it.
-然后带着大家离开这里 -明白了
Shion-dono!
士远大人
We'll talk later. I'll finish this quickly!
我们之后再说 我会迅速解决掉这个
The way the waves are moving…
这些波的动向
The smell, the sounds… There's no mistaking it.
气味、声音 不会弄错的
It's similar to what Tenza faced!
这和天座所面对的情况相似
On the journey here, I studied the life forces of the monsters…
在前往这里的旅途中 我研究了怪物的生命力
The quality of their waves and how they use them.
它们的波特性以及它们的运用方法
A magic for destroying their immortality…
一种摧毁它们的不朽魔法
I will test my idea on you.
我要在你身上试验我的想法
If I slash at your waves directly, vital point or not, I may kill you.
如果我直接斩击你的波 无论是否是要害 我都可能会杀死你
Like cutting directly though the soul…
就像直接切入灵魂一样
It will free the waves…
它会释放波
Work it into a circle… And wrap myself up in it.
将其形成一个圆圈 然后我将自己包裹其中
The flower transformation stopped… But at this point…
花朵的转化停止了 但到了这一步…
Hoko, what should we do?
树人 我们该怎么办？
There is nothing I can do.
我无能为力
I did not even know Lord Tensen's true form.
我甚至不知道天仙大人的原型
Out of the way, you two.
让开 你们两个
It might be too late, but I have a salve that can staunch the bleeding.
或许已经太晚了 但我有一种可以止血的药膏
Yuzu… ri… ha…
杠
I'm… already…
我已经…
Shion-dono!
士远大人！
Don't worry about my master. He's super-strong.
不要担心我的师父 他超级强大
Besides, we were chasing someone before we found you.
而且在找到你们之前 我们正在追踪一个人
We can't die here.
我们不能死在这里
Tameshi Itto-ryu: Demon Rain.
试验一刀流：鬼雨
Tameshi Itto-ryu: Long Autumn Rains.
试验一刀流：长秋雨
What the heck? That guy is amazing!
什么？那个家伙太厉害了
That's my master!
那是我的师父！
It's not regenerating…
它没有再生了
Is Shion-dono's Tao compatible with the enemy's?
士远大人的道能与敌人的兼容吗？
At this rate…
按照这样的速度…
It's mostly as I expected.
大部分都是我所预料的
Awesome. You're a match for me too?
太棒了 你也和我实力相当？
However…
然而…
Even a scratch from us will start Florification!
即使只被我们伤到一点 也会开始花化
You will become excellent Tan!
你将变成极好的棕褐色
Master!
师父！
You too… wish to die?
你也想死吗？
I have no intention of dying here.
我并不打算死在这里
But if I must die to continue on my path, then I don't mind!
但如果是为了继续我的道路而死去 我也无所谓！
What's with that guy?
那个家伙是怎么回事？
He's terrifying!
他太可怕了
He's going to die of blood loss…
他会失血过多而亡
Master…
师父
Kill. Kill him!
杀 杀掉他
It's using the waves just as I thought,
正如我所料 它在用波
but ordinary methods won't work.
但普通的方法不起作用
I need a plan to take out this immortal… But will my body hold up?
我需要一个能够消灭这个不朽的计划 但是我的身体能够承受得住吗？
We have to help…
我们必须去帮忙
Don't! You can hardly stand!
不要 你们都站不住了
But… at this rate…
但这样下去的话…
No. Shion-dono is already prepared to die.
不 士远大人已经准备好赴死了
He doesn't stand a chance fighting alone…
他一个人战斗的话 机会不大
Let's at least make a second group and make an opening for him.
我们至少组成第二组 为他创造一个机会
Fine.
好吧
-Then let's all do it together. -What?!
-那我们一起做吧 -什么？
Give me a break! I'm at the end of my strength!
别逗了 我已经快要筋疲力尽了
I see…
明白了
-Is that better? -Is what better?
-现在好一点了吗？ -什么好一点了？
That's weird…
奇怪
Are you better now?
你现在好一点了吗？
A little bit of my strength came back…
我的力量稍微恢复了一些
Are you better?
你感觉好些了吗？
Um, well, yeah… But how?
但是为什么？
My grandpa used to do this all the time. I tried it on my master
我爷爷经常这么做 我试过用在我的师父身上
and he said he felt better…
他说感觉好多了
My strength feels very much recovered.
我感觉力量恢复了很多
The waves are in all things,
波存在于万物之中
but maybe they have different compatibilities…
但可能有着不同的兼容性
Like the five elements of Chinese medicine.
就像中医的五行一样
But don't embrace someone so suddenly.
但是不要突然拥抱别人
Its effects are strong enough with just a touch.
它的效果只需轻触就足够强大
Okay!
好的！
Does that mean Tao can be compatible, like one can raise the other's?
这是否意味着道兼容 彼此可以互相提升？
No… Now is not the time to think about it.
不 现在不是考虑这个的时候
If I can move, then that's enough.
如果我能动 那就足够了
-Let's go! -Good luck!
-我们走 -祝你们好运
Sagiri, Nurugai, didn't I tell you to run?
佐切、濡亥 我不是让你们快跑吗？
Wait… what happened to you?
等等 你们怎么了？
We're reinforcements, Shion-dono.
我们是增援 士远大人
I know its weakness.
我知道它的弱点
Its weakness?
它的弱点？
The source of its power… It's the Tanden.
它力量的源泉就是丹田
Hit its core, and it should die.
击中它的核心 它就会死去
But… This creature has two Tandens…
但是这个生物有两个丹田
And more importantly, if it even scratches you, it's fatal.
更重要的是 它只要擦伤你一下 就会致命
That's why we've done this.
所以我们才做了这个
We've covered ourselves in bandages and this mucus from Yuzuriha.
我们用绷带 和杠的胶水把自己裹了起来
We should be able to avoid scratches and thus Florification.
我们应该能够避免擦伤 从而避免花化
Do you have to lick it?
一定要舔吗？
Nope.
并不用
The child and I will team up and take on the front.
我和这孩子会组成一个团队对付前方
While we do that, please take the back.
在我们这样做的同时 请你负责后方
With the speed of your blade, we can strike two places at once.
凭借你出剑的速度 我们可以同时攻击两个地方
Watch out!
小心！
That physical ability is impressive…
它的体能真是厉害
Wow!
哇
Sagiri can also sense the waves…
佐切也能感知波
Like me, she predicts the enemy's movements from the flow of the waves.
和我一样 她可以根据波的流动 预测敌人的动作
With even more precision and speed than me…
比我更精确、更快
You've become stronger…
你变得更强了
I'm sorry.
对不起
Let's do your plan, Sagiri!
按照你的计划行动 佐切
-Let us proceed with expediency! -Alright!
-我们迅速前进吧 -好！
Tameshi Itto-ryu:
试验一刀流：
Autumn Shower!
秋雨
They're actually overpowering it! Wow…
他们居然压制住它了 哇
It's taking longer and longer to regenerate.
它用来再生的时间越来越长
I've never seen Shion-dono so fierce.
我从来没见过士远大人如此凶猛
At this rate… we can win.
这样下去 我们能赢
Keep up… the pace…
保持节奏
Even if I have to die here…
即使我要在这里死去…
I'm sorry, Sagiri, Nurugai…
对不起 佐切、濡亥
I knew it would put you in danger…
我知道这会让你们陷入危险
But there's no way to stop now!
但现在已经停不下来了
This murky sensation is covering my head…
这种混浊的感觉笼罩着我的头脑
My whole body.
我的整个身体
This is a hatred I was not prepared for.
这是我没有准备好的仇恨
Hatred and frustration are things I cannot allow.
我不能容忍仇恨和沮丧
I will never forgive myself
我永远不会原谅自己
for that time I had no choice but to run.
当时我别无选择 只能逃跑
I'll never forgive you! I'll never forgive you! I'll never forgive you!
我永远不会原谅你
Yamada Asaemon Shion, I will never forgive you!
山田浅右卫门士远 我永远都不会原谅你！
Not until you end the life of your enemy.
除非你结束敌人的生命
Not until your own life ends!
除非你的生命结束！
Shion-dono!
士远大人！
Collect all of the waves of your body in one place…
将你身体的所有波汇聚到一处
As if tempering it… As if wearing it… On your blade…
如同调和一样 如同覆盖在剑上一般
Collecting the waves is like collecting your soul.
汇聚波就像汇聚你的灵魂一样
If you do it poorly, you may die.
如果做得不好 就有可能死亡
Since you are immortal, I will teach you.
因为你是不朽的 所以我会教你
The transience of life… The heaviness of it…
生命的短暂、生命的沉重…
The terror of it!
生命的恐怖！
Wait…
等等
Is this really its weakness?
这真的是它的弱点吗？
Sagiri said it was the source of its power…
佐切说这是它力量的源泉
But I don't feel any strong waves…
但我感觉不到任何强大的波
-No time to hesitate! -Shion!
-没有时间犹豫了 -士远！
It's the ovule!
是胚珠！
Senta?!
仙汰？
The plant… monsters…
这些植物…怪物
Their Tanden is the ovule!
它们的丹田就是胚珠！
The place where… the flower collects its nutrients…
植物从中吸取养分的地方
The center… of the flower petals…
花瓣的中心
That's where it's weakest!
那里是它最薄弱的地方！
So beautiful…
好美啊
The shape of someone prepared for death… The space between life and death…
一个准备面对死亡的人的样子 生与死之间的空间
We cannot reach it…
我们无法触及
A perfect balance of Yin and Yang…
阴阳的完美平衡
I want to tell Rien…
我想告诉莲…
I've been waiting a thousand years… Thank you…
我已经等待了一千年 谢谢
Senta-dono!
仙汰大人
He doesn't have much time left.
他没多少时间了
That took everything he had…
那耗尽了他所有的力量
No!
不
-Senta! -Master, don't move!
-仙汰！ -师父 不要动
Where's that ointment?
那个药膏在哪里？
I have enough for one more person…
我只剩下一份
Well then…
那么…
I think we should use it on him…
我想我们应该用在他身上
Can't we divide it?
我们不能分一点吗？
I need some for myself too.
我自己也需要一些
I'm not a nice enough person to give it all away.
我不是一个好人 把它全部都给出去
Besides, with what comes next,
还有 接下来会发生什么
we can't be carrying around an injured person. Let it go.
我们不能带着一个受伤的人 放手吧
No…
不
But… that's…
但那是…
Didn't you say that as long as we're alive,
你不是说只要我们活着
we'll manage?
我们就能应付吗？
Ninjas are realistic.
忍者是现实的
We know the difference between
我们知道值得
a challenge worth taking and a challenge that isn't.
和不值得去迎接的挑战
I think you already know…
我想你已经知道了
you can't be saved.
我不会救你
So you don't need them.
所以你不需要它们
Your role and your samurai pride…
你的角色和你的武士荣誉
You don't need them anymore.
你不再需要它们了
Just… rest easy now.
现在 放松就可以了
You've lied to yourself your whole life, right?
你一生都在欺骗自己 对吧？
So why not, at the very end, be true to you…
所以为什么不在最后对自己坦诚
And think only about the things you love.
只关注你爱的事物
Your family… Your pet cat…
你的家人、你的宠物猫
Someone you loved in your hometown?
故乡你爱的人？
Imagine what it's like to be in that person's heart
想象身处那个人的心中
so you can die in a beautiful place.
这样你就能在一个美丽的地方死去
I'll lend you my arm, if you need it.
如果需要的话 我可以把手臂借给你
Things I love… My family back home… Sugar candy stars…
我爱的东西 我家乡的家人、糖果星星
A book of Kitao Shigemasa's art…
一本北尾重政的艺术书
In the heart of someone I admire…
在我崇拜的人的心中…
It seems the circumstances have changed rapidly.
情况似乎发生了很大的变化
I'd like to regroup for a moment.
我想稍微整理一下
I agree. First, who the heck are you guys?
我同意 首先 你们到底是谁？
Let's get away from here first. Sagiri?
我们先离开这里吧 佐切？
Thank you for earlier, Yuzuriha.
谢谢你之前的帮助 杠
Once again, your composure saved the day.
你的沉着冷静又一次拯救了我们
Sinners and executioners don't matter anymore.
是罪人还是处刑人不再重要
If it did, we wouldn't survive.
如果重要的话 我们不会活下来
We must…
我们必须
focus on surviving and going home.
专注于生存和回家
I won't let anyone else die.
我不会再让任何人死去
We will all survive, and we will all get off the island.
我们都会活下来 我们都会离开这个岛屿
We will.
我们会的
That's what you do as soon as you wake up?
这是你一醒来就要做的事吗？
What are you, a cat? You're too alert.
你是猫吗？你太警觉了
Where are we?
我们在哪里？
We're in a cave halfway up the mountain.
我们在山上的一个洞穴里
I carried you up here.
我把你背到这里来的
I can't remember…
我不记得了
I think we can hide here for a bit.
我想我们可以在这里躲一会儿
We'll still need to be on alert, of course.
当然 我们仍然需要保持警惕
What are you doing?
你在做什么？
I'm changing.
我在换衣服
Sagirin, try this one on!
佐切 试试这件
Me too!
我也要
Why would a boy wear this?
男生为什么要穿这个？
Y… you--
你…
Settle down!
安静点！
Sagiri…
佐切
I understand why you feel on edge,
我理解你为什么感到紧张
but you all must be very tired.
但你们一定都很累了
No punishment will strike if you let your guard down a bit.
你稍微放松警惕也不会受到惩罚
Shion-dono…
士远大人
-Yeah. -Here, hold it for a sec.
-好的 -给 帮我拿一下
Alright, everyone…
好了 各位
whatever you're doing, just listen for moment.
不管你们在做什么 请听我说一下
Okay!
好！
In order to survive, we need to sort out the necessary information.
为了生存 我们需要整理必要的信息
First of all, using the waves against Lord Tensen.
首先 利用波对抗天仙
What you call "Tao".
你们所说的“道”
Everyone naturally possesses the power,
每个人天生都拥有这种力量
but if you can manage to use it, you can attain superhuman abilities.
但如果你能够运用它 你就能获得超人的能力
You've experienced it, Sagiri.
你已经经历过了 佐切
Your Tao has grown stronger after everything you've experienced.
在你经历过一切之后 你的道变得更强大了
It must… have been hard.
这一定很辛苦
Well… I'm sure it was for you too.
我敢肯定对你来说也是这样
But it's dangerous to misuse it.
但滥用它是危险的
Tao is your actual life force.
道是你真正的生命力
If you use too much, it won't just exhaust you.
如果你使用过多 后果不只筋疲力尽这么简单
I don't know what the effects are exactly, but…
我不知道确切的影响是什么 但是
It could cause abnormalities in your spirit or body…
它可能会使你的精神或身体产生异常
Or your awareness… For example, it could affect your memories.
或者你的意识 比如它可能会影响你的记忆
Or in the worst case, lead to death.
或者最糟糕的情况 导致死亡
If you're going to go on about life and death…
如果你要谈论生死
We have another serious problem.
我们还有另一个严重的问题
The Elixir of Immortality.
长生不老药
They said they have something,
他们说他们有什么东西
but it's not an elixir of immortality.
但那不是长生不老药
The government won't accept that it doesn't exist.
幕府不会接受它不存在
Gabimaru said it existed…
画眉丸说它是存在的
That his village chief was immortal.
他的村长是不朽的
It must exist somewhere…
它一定存在于某个地方
About that…
关于那个
I think that might've been an illusion.
我觉得那可能是一种幻术
An… illusion?
幻术？
Yeah, like the magic arts ninjas use.
是 就像那种忍者使用的幻术
They show little kids supernatural displays
他们向小孩子展示超自然的景象
to install total domination over them.
以便对他们进行绝对的控制
In the long run they instill the idea that the chief can never be opposed.
从长远来看 他们灌输的观念是 永远不能反抗村长
Only a few of the upper echelon know the truth.
只有上层少数人知道真相
My village was the same way.
我的村庄也是一样的
What?
什么？
There were some other things that bothered me too.
还有一些其他的事情也让我感到困扰
Sagirin, you said
佐切 你说
that Gabimaru is here for the sake of the person he loves.
画眉丸是为了他爱的人才来到这里
Yes, his wife…
是的 他的妻子
That to me is kind of weird.
对我来说这有点奇怪
Ninjas are just tools. A woman might get married at that age,
忍者只是工具 一个女人也许会在这个年龄结婚
but would a man so young have a spouse?
但一个如此年轻的男人会有配偶吗？
For example,
比如
a person wouldn't be reeled in with just fear, right?
一个人不会只被恐惧所迷惑 对吧？
If you want them to face death for you,
如果你希望他们为你面对死亡
you have to give them some other motivation.
你必须给他们其他的动力
-I'm just guessing here. -Ho…
-我只是猜测 -呃…
-Hold on… -Our villages.
-等等… -我们的村庄
They're different, of course.
跟他们的不一样 这是自然
But… You know…
但你知道…
I can't remember.
我记不得了
Has something blocked my memories?
我的记忆被什么东西封锁了吗？
Gabimaru's… wife?
画眉丸的妻子？
Does she actually exist?
她真的存在吗？
Hold on…
等等
What's her name?
她叫什么名字？
-Have you seen her? -Please…
-你见过她吗？ -拜托
Couldn't it be some kind of long-term magic?
难道这是某种长期的魔法吗？
I mean… Can he even tell you what she looks like?
我是说 他能告诉你她长什么样吗？
I can't…
我不记得
Where even am I? Why am I here?
我现在在哪里？我为什么在这里？
Who are these people?
这些人是谁？
Enemies…? I don't think so…
敌人？我想不是
I know who I am.
我知道我是谁
I am
我是
Chief of the Iwagakure People, Gabimaru the Hollow.
石隐村的首领 空洞的画眉丸
I'll have to start by talking to these people and collecting information.
我必须从和这些人交谈开始收集信息
If my secrets get out…
如果我的秘密泄露出去…
Gabimaru… are you okay?
画眉丸 你还好吗？
Yeah. I'm fine.
我没事
Aren't you going to sleep, Sagiri?
佐切 你还不打算睡觉吗？
Shion…dono?
士远大人？
What are you wearing?
你穿的是什么？
I changed, since I was covered in blood.
我换了衣服 因为那件衣服上都是血
It wasn't a very good "look".
这不是一个很好的“形象”
I thought I finally found someone who understood my jokes.
我还以为 我终于找到能理解我笑话的人了
Maybe my delivery was bad…
也许是我的表演有问题
No, it was exactly as it should be.
不 就应该这样的
It's just… Right now, I just…
只是…现在 我只是…
Eizen-dono, Genji-dono, Senta-dono, Kisho-dono,
卫善大人、源嗣大人 仙汰大人、期圣大人
even Tenza-dono… So much has happened…
就连典坐大人也…发生了这么多事
but it's only the third night…
现在才是第三个晚上
And Gabimaru… I have no idea what happened to him.
还有画眉丸 我不知道他怎么了
Sagiri…
佐切
-Are you in love-- -No, not at all.
-你是不是爱上… -完全没有
You shouldn't see everything as a love affair.
你不应该把一切都视为爱情故事
Sorry.
对不起
But it's clear you feel some way about him.
但你明显对他有感觉
Enough to change your point of view.
足以改变你的观点
What is Gabimaru to you?
对你来说 画眉丸是什么人？
Honestly… I don't really know. But…
老实说 我真的不知道 但是
To be born in a village of murderers,
在一个由杀手组成的村庄出生
continuously ordered to kill…
不断被命令去杀人
Even if you know love,
即使你懂得爱
it's just torture for your past self.
也只是对过去的自己的折磨
And on top of that, if, like Yuzuriha said,
而且如果像杠说的那样
even your motive ends up a deception…
连你的动力都是骗人的
That's just… That's just so sad…
那就…那就太可悲了
He is a vicious murderer.
他是一个凶残的杀手
He is, but… I don't think he's a bad person.
是的 但我不认为他是个坏人
That's why…
这就是为什么…
I believe they will reunite.
我相信他们会团聚
He would never give up.
他绝不会放弃
He would survive, and make it back.
他会活着回去
HOTEL OHASHI
（旅笼大桥）
I will now read a message from the Shogun.
现在我来宣读将军的消息
Listen carefully.
请仔细听好
I hereby order the House of Yamada to depart again for Shinsenkyo
我特此命令山田家再次前往神仙境
and monitor those who have alighted on the island.
监视那些登岛的人
I have selected a suitable leader.
我已经选定了一名合适的领导者
Yamada Asaemon Shugen.
山田浅右卫门殊现
Subtitle translation by: Dale Angles
字幕翻译：朱未耒